Guide to the Amelia MacDonald Cutler Papers, 1906-1921
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Amelia MacDonald Cutler Papers
1906-1921
Cutler, Amelia MacDonald, 1882-1947
0.30 cubic feet (63 items in 1 box)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Papers concerning her interest in woman suffrage and including letters from Anna De Baun, John M. Glenn, Norval D. Kemp, Henrietta W. Livermore, Caroline Ruutz-Rees, Anna Howard Shaw, and Vira Boarman Whitehouse, 1908-1917; one letter from Cutler to Livermore, 1916; two letters about Cutler from Carrie Chapman Catt and Norval D. Kemp, 1908-1916; clippings, programs, and other miscellaneous printed matter on suffrage work, 1916-1921; and manuscripts and typescripts by Cutler on rural life and people, 1906-1917.
Biographical Note
Amelia Shaw Macdonald was born in Delhi, New York on September 28, 1882, the daughter of John Thompson and Catherine Coville MacDonald. Miss MacDonald entered Vassar College with the Class of 1904 and received her degree in 1907. On March 2, 1909, she married Charles Evelyn Cutler, a landscape architect, and the two took up residence in Westport, Connecticut.
Following her graduation from Vassar, Amelia became involved in the woman's suffrage movement. She was a member of the board of the League of Women Voters and acted as an advisor to the National American Woman Suffrage Movement as well as the New York State Commission on Country Life. Amelia was particularly dedicated to the suffrage movement in rural areas, being convinced that the achievement of woman's suffrage in farming communities was essential to the improvement of country life on the whole.
In addition to her suffragist activities, Amelia MacDonald Cutler expressed a keen interest in the restoration of farmhouse and colonial architecture types, with an emphasis on the preservation of historical landmarks that figured in Pre-Revolution days. Her knowledge of historical architecture was once described as being "exhaustive." She was also highly recognized for her contributions to the conservation of Connecticut state forests and wildflower life. She was active in the Westport Garden Club and was elected chairman of the New England Wildflower Preservation Society, a position she would hold until her death on February 16, 1947.
Scope and Content Note
The Amelia MacDonald Cutler Collection contains correspondence, manuscripts, and printed materials related exclusively to her involvement in the Women's Suffrage Movement. There is no information dealing with her interest in landscape architecutre and historical preservation.
The Collection consists chiefly of correspondence. Letters are arranged alphabetically by author. The 47 letters written to Cutler span from 1908 to 1917, and deal with the various papers and articles that she wrote to improve rural conditions and further the suffrage movement.
A set of 34 letters written between Cutler and Lucy Maynard Salmon (1908-1924) together with 2 letters written by Adelaide Underhill can be found within the Lucy Maynard Salmon Collection at Vassar College. These letters cover a broader range of topics than do those contained within the Cutler Collection, including personal matters, wildflower preservation, and landscape architecture.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Subject Headings
Names:
De Baun, Anna; Glenn, John M.; Kemp, Norval D.; Livermore, Henrietta Jackson Wells, b. 1864; Ruutz-Rees, Caroline, 1865-; Shaw, Anna Howard, 1847-1919; Whitehouse, Vira Boarman, 1875-1957; Catt, Carrie Chapman, 1859-1947
Subjects:
Women--Suffrage; Women's rights; Farm life; Country life; Rural women--Social conditions; Women social reformers
VCL Categories
Women's History
Encoding Information
Encoded by Elizabeth Clarke, November 2006.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Amelia MacDonald Cutler.
Series List
- SERIES I. CORRESPONDENCE
- SERIES II. TYPESCRIPTS and MANUSCRIPTS
- SERIES III. PRINTED MATERIAL
- SERIES IV. FRAGMENTS
Container List
- SERIES I. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Letters to Amelia MacDonald Cutler
    - Cutler, Janer (daughter) VC 1934, (1 letter) (Folder 1.1)
    - DeBaun, Anna, 1915-1917; (3 letters) (Folder 1.1A)
    - Glenn, John M., 1908-1909; (3 letters) (Folder 1.2)
    - Kemp, Norval D., 1908-1909; (8 letters) (Folder 1.3)
    - Livermore, Henrietta W., 1916, n.d.; (6 letters, 1 w/ draft of reply) (Folder 1.4)
    - Ruutz-Rees, Caroline, 1915; (4 letters) (Folder 1.5)
    - Shaw, Anna Howard, 1915; (3 letters) (Folder 1.6)
    - Whitehouse, Vira Boarman, 1916; (4 letters) (Folder 1.7)
    - Minor correspondence, 1908-1917, n.d.; (16 letters) (Folder 1.8)
  - Letters from Amelia MacDonald Cutler
    - To Henrietta W. Livermore, 1916; (1 letter) (Folder 1.9)
    - To Marie Maples Preson, VC 1900, (1 letter) (Folder 1.9A)
  - Letters about Amelia MacDonald Cutler
    - Letter from Carrie Chapman Catt to Lucy Maynard Salmon; from Norval D. Kemp to John M. Glenn, 1908-1916; (2 letters) (Folder 1.10)
    - Doctor's excuse for Amelia Cutler, with Cutler's [?] drawing, 1902; (1 item) (Folder 1.10A)
- SERIES II. TYPESCRIPTS AND MANUSCRIPTS BY CUTLER
  - "Social Conditions Among the Country Folk of New York State,", [1906]; (TS, 14 p. ) (Folder 1.11)
  - "Farm Women and Insanity,", [1915]; (TS, 6 p. ) (Folder 1.12)
  - "Reciprocity with Canada,", [ca 1916]; (MS, 8 p. ) (Folder 1.13)
  - "How to Reach the Rural Voters,", [1917]; (MS, 18 p. ) (Folder 1.14)
  - "How to Reach the Rural Voters," (partial typescript), [1917]; (TS, 5 p. ) (Folder 1.15)
- SERIES III. PRINTED MATERIALS
  - News articles concerning Cutler's suffrage activities (photocopy), 1916, n.d.; (3 articles) (Folder 1.16)
  - Miscellaneous printed materials, 1921, n.d.; (1 flyer, 2 programs) (Folder 1.17)
  - Cutler Memorial and Genealogical History, 1989 (Folder 1.17A)
- SERIES IV. FRAGMENTS
  - Description of documents contained within the Cutler Collection, n.d.; (1 item) (Folder 1.18)